Finding Aid for the Peter Plagens papers LSC.2255
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Writing, 1970-2012
  - Art Writing - Misc., 2000-2003 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    Materials include an Art in America memorial for John Coplans, a juror's statement for the Huntington Museum of Art's "Exhibition 280," a "Cents and Sensibility: Collecting the '80s" Artforum article and a "How Art Has Changed a Lot" essay for American Art.
  - Art Writing, 2004-2006 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    Materials include the following: "Objects in mirror are more distant than they appear," Plagens' look back at "The Boys' Club" Los Angeles art scene of the 1960s and 1970s, "The Scene Changes: New York Art in the Postwar Decades," New England Review essay and "Return of the white cube," ArtReview article concerning Brian O'Doherty's "Inside the White Cube" lecture.
  - Art Writing, 2007-2009 (Box 8, Folder 10-11)
    Materials include an Art in America memorial for Walter Gabrielson, Common Review essay, "The Absolute Truth About Art," a New England Review "Another Look at Clement Greenberg" essay, and the "Turner's Magic Mountains" ARTnews review of the J.M.W. Turner retrospective.
  - Kuntz, 2007 (Box 8, Folder 12-13)
    Materials include clippings, timelines, correspondence, a CD and annotated drafts of his essay on Roger Kuntz for the Laguna Art Museum's Kuntz retrospective catalogue.
    1 CD
  - Art Writing, 2010 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    Materials include annotated typescripts such as "Pacific Standard Revise," Plagens' review of the Getty's Pacific Standard Time: Los Angeles Art 1945-1980 book, a Smithsonian Magazine article on painter Clyfford Still and the Denver museum in his name and the New England Review essay "Leo Castelli and the New World."
  - Eye Level: A in A, 2010-2012 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    Materials include annotated typescripts and published clippings from Plagens' Eye Level articles for Art in America.
  - Art Writing Notes, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
    Materials include notes on John Coplans, Artforum, and the pleasure of reading.
  - Art Writing: In the Hopper, circa 2010 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    Materials include an annotated typescript concerning Eli Broad's installation of Jeffrey Deitch as director of Los Angeles' Museum of Contemporary Art (MoCA) and the museum's future.
  - Art Writing Unpublished, undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
    Materials include typescripts on San Francisco's Ant Farm, comedian Eddie Izzard, David Hockney's Secret Knowledge book and an interview with art critic Hilton Kramer.
  - A.W. Press & Publicity, circa 2000 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    This "News From Hudson Hills Press" release announces its monograph on minimalist Tony DeLap, written by Bruce Guenther and Peter Plagens.
  - Art Writing: Reviews (of), 1974-1975, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    Materials include reviews of Moonlight Blues: An Artist's Art Criticism and Sunshine Muse: Contemporary Art on the West Coast.
  - Art Writing, undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
    Materials include annotated typescripts concerning sculptor John Chamberlain, painter Malcolm Morley, the Getty's Pacific Standard Time: Los Angeles Art, 1945-1980 catalogue and Hunter Drohojowksa's book, Rebels in Paradise: The L.A. Art Scene and the 1960s.
  - Anthology Book, 1995 (Box 9, Folder 9-12)
    Materials include Plagens' clippings and annotated typescripts of his unpublished art criticism. This unpublished Anthology Book was to include Plagens' art criticism from various publications. Folder 10 also contains the following six slides: 1) Durham, N.C. 2) The VW bus on I-85 north 3) Traffic stall, I-85 north 4) The Black Truck near Amarillo, TX 5) Dunes, California desert, and 6) Truck terminal opposite Linden's loft, LA.
  - Art Writing floppies, 1988-2001 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    Six floppy disks include published criticism, notes and research.
    Six 3.5-inch floppy disks
  - Painting audio cassette and floppy disk, undated (Box 9, Folder 14)
    The audio cassette tape includes audio notes for what Plagens describes as "... a thinky memoir about being an abstract painter." Plagens was in the habit of carrying around a cassette recorder and recording thoughts as they occurred.
    One 3.5-inch floppy disk and one audio cassette.
  - Art Writing: Newsweek, 1989-2003 (Box 11, Folder 1-3, Box 10, Folder 1-11)
    Materials include photocopies of clippings from Plagens' work as Newsweek's art critic. Box 11, Folder 1 contains two floppy disks of Newsweek drafts.
    Two 3.5-inch floppy disks
  - Critical Mess book, 2006 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    One copy of Critical Mess: Art Critics on the State of their Practice, edited by Raphael Rubinstein includes Plagens' "At a Crossroads" essay and is signed by Rubinstein and fellow essayists Katy Siegel, Thomas McEvilley, Nancy Princenthal and Eleanor Heartney.
  - Merciful Brief novel and screenplay, 1972, 2002 (Box 12, Folder 1-5)
    These folders contain three photocopies of Plagens' unpublished novel set in Los Angeles and two copies of the screenplay. Folder 4 includes correspondence between Plagens and the Smithsonian's Archives of American Art reference services interlibrary loan coordinator concerning searching his papers for a copy of the manuscript and screenplay.
  - West Coast Art, circa 1972 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    Plagens' West Coast Art manuscript was revised and published in 1974 as Sunshine Muse: Contemporary Art on the West Coast, his first book of art criticism and history which set the stage for the Getty's Pacific Standard Time initiative. This book was published again as Sunshine Muse: Art on the West Coast, 1945-1970 by University of California Press in 1999 with a new introduction by Plagens.
  - Sunshine Muse, 1999-2000 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    Materials include royalty statements, correspondence from University of California Press Paperback Editor Charlene Woodcock, images of cover painting Figure on a Porch by Richard Diebenkorn, a photccopy of the Memorandum of Agreement between Peter Plagens and The Regents of the University of California, text for the book's spine and back cover, correspondence to Judy Throm of Reference Services at the Smithsonian Archives of American Art concerning photographs and transparencies for the book's new edition and reviews of the first edition.
  - Sunshine Muse floppy disk, 2002 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    This floppy disk includes one Sunshine Muse folder.
  - Sunshine Muse photos (Box 14, Folder 1-16)
    These black and white photographs were published in the book.
  - Sunshine Muse illustration releases, 1973-1974 (Box 14, Folder 17-18)
    Folder 17 contains one set of signed illustration releases and folder 18 contains one set of unsigned illustration releases.
  - Robo: Clips (Box 15, Folder 1-2)
    Plagens used these research clippings while writing his first novel, Time for Robo. Clippings are numbered and arranged by the following headings: Physics (Macro/Micro), Espionage (Crime), Religion (Prophets/Gurus), Art (Authorship) (See Writing), Writing (Emptying Mind), Time, Theory, Air Craft and Sport (Body). Materials also include notecards on voice, language and the novel's structure.
  - Robo: Notes (Box 15, Folder 3)
    Materials include Excel spreadsheet print outs of the novel's chronology, notes on characters, style and plot themes and a four page "Whom I hate:" typescript.
  - Time for Robo: Press, 1998-2000 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    Press clippings and lists of publications with contacts for book reviews.
  - Time for Robo, 1996 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    Plagens' copy of his book publishing agreement and an Excel spreadsheet print out of notes for the novel.
  - Time for Robo, undated (Box 15, Folder 6-7)
    Typescript of novel annotated by Plagens.
  - Time for Robo: Book Itself, 1996-1998 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    Correspondence between Plagens and Black Heron Press publisher Jerry Gold and an advance copy of the book jacket. In his introductory letter to Gold, Plagens describes Time for Robo as follows: "... a small part of it is about art. But the book is really about time, perception, and a few questions concerning reality...."
  - Time for Robo, 1999 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    One hardcover copy of the novel signed by the author.
  - Robo Notes (Box 16, Folder 1-2)
    Photocopies of clippings, used by Plagens while conducting research for this novel.
  - Robo: Adds (Box 16, Folder 3)
    Materials include Plagens' handwritten notes, clippings, photocopies of articles and two slides of Dieric Bouts' paintings: The Altarpiece of the Last Supper and The Martyrdom of St. Hippolytus.
  - Robo 2 (Box 17, Folder 1-2)
    Typescript entitled Robo 2, The Synquel: Noam Sain and the Altadena Bungalow.
  - For Book 2 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    Materials include a photocopy of "Intrusions?" by J. W. Dunne.
  - Robo 2 stuff (Box 17, Folder 4-5)
    Clippings concerning villains and cults.
  - Robo 2 Notes (Box 17, Folder 6-7)
    Materials include clippings, photocopies of articles, chronologies, title ideas, to do lists, lists of words, character descriptions, main points and themes such as Words vs. Reality and Science vs. Religion.
  - ATKDRWNAOH (Box 17, Folder 8)
    Initials stand for Among Those Killed in the Dawn Raid Was Noam, Aged One Hundred. This folder contains one Post-It with a note about Noam confronted, surrounded and stabbed by pachucos in the 1950s.
  - Robo 2 floppies (Box 17, Folder 9)
    Thirteen floppy disks include notes and multiple drafts.
    Thirteen 3.5-inch floppy disks
  - Robo 2 CD (Box 17, Folder 10)
    One CD includes draft 6 for printing.
  - Noam Sain and the Altadena Bungalow (Box 18, Folder 1-2)
    One Robo 2 typescript.
  - Robo 3 Notes (Box 18, Folder 3)
    Materials for Plagens' third Robo novel include handwritten research titles and corresponding page numbers, clippings and photocopies from Brad and Sherry Steiger's dossier, Conspiracies and Secret Societies.
  - Robo 3 (Box 18, Folder 4-7)
    Four copies of Plagens' third Robo novel are titled, Robo 3: Among Those Killed in the Dawn Raid Was the Reverend Noam Sain, Aged One Hundred.
  - Robo 3 floppies (Box 18, Folder 8)
    Two floppy disks include chapters in outline format and a first draft of the novel.
  - Lieutenant Kao (Box 19, Folder 1-4)
    Two copies of Plagens' unpublished novel that tells the story of a kamikaze pilot who survives and ends up as a houseboy in a sorority house.
  - Lt. Kao Japan (Box 19, Folder 5-6)
    Research materials for the novel include photocopies of articles and print-outs from the internet concerning Japanese history.
  - Lt. Kao U.S. (Box 19, Folder 7)
    Research materials for the novel include clippings, email correspondence with sorority sisters, print outs of internet articles on Japanese American history in Los Angeles, the story's chronology, stream of consciousness notes by a sorority sister on Greek letter organizations and a "50th Anniversary of the Founding of Alpha Tau Omega Fraternity" booklet, Plagens' USC fraternity.
  - Lt. Kao floppies, circa 2000-2002 (Box 19, Folder 8)
    Three floppy disks include drafts, notes and business materials.
    Three 3.5-inch floppy disks
  - Confessions of a Fellatrix, undated (Box 20, Folder 1)
    One copy of Plagens' unpublished novel/memoir hybrid.
  - N3 floppies, 2005-2006 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    Versions of Plagens' unpublished Novel 3, a novel/memoir hybrid entitled Confessions of a Fellatrix.
    Eight 3.5-inch floppy disks
  - The Art Critic, circa 2008 (Box 20, Folder 3-9)
    Folders 3-6 contain three photocopied manuscripts of Plagens' online novel, which was first published as a serial in 24 weekly installments by Artnet, and then again in 2012 by Hol Art Books. Folders 7 and 8 contain a draft with Laurie Fendrich's edits and annotations and folder 9 contains nine floppy disks of various drafts.
    Nine 3.5-inch floppy disks
  - TAC - Rewrite, circa 2008 (Box 21, Folder 1-3)
    Folders 1 and 2 include the original copy of the manuscript with Laurie Fendrich's edits and annotations as well as some notes by Plagens. Folder 3 includes two floppy disks with rewrites of Plagens' second novel and raw material.
  - TAC e-book shelf surrogate, 2012 (Box 36, Folder 7)
    This shelf surrogate consists of a color copy of the novel's cover, back and spine, a bookmark and tassel. These materials were created by Hol Art Books and include instructions for assembly. The text on the bookmark reads: "The critic's job is to prevent the next Jeff Koons or Mark Kostabi from gaining a fucking foothold."
  - Nauman research/notes, 2008-2009 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    Materials concerning Plagens' book, Bruce Nauman: The True Artist, include questions for interviews with Connie Lewallen, John Baldessari, Frank Owen, Brenda Richardson and Jane Livingston, Plagens' handwritten notes on Nauman's life and William T. Wiley's handwritten responses to Plagens concerning his work with Nauman at UC Davis.
  - Nauman - Chronologies (Box 22, Folder 2)
    Plagens' typed chronology covers Nauman's life and work from 1941-2009.
  - Nauman draft (Box 22, Folder 3)
    Early draft of the Nauman manuscript with annotations and a photocopy of the Leo Castelli Gallery catalog for Nauman's first one-man exhibition in New York.
  - Nauman manuscript, circa 2009 (Box 22, Folder 4-8)
    Multiple versions of the Nauman manuscript. Folders 5 and 6 include corrections by Bruce Nauman and Angela Westwater. Folder 7 includes a copy of the manuscript on a CD for Phaidon Press.
  - Bruce Nauman in Venice, 2009 (Box 22, Folder 9)
    Press releases, image sheets, Nauman biography/bibliography and exhibition venue maps comprise Plagens' folder for Bruce Nauman: Topological Gardens, the official United States representation at the 53rd International Art Exhibition -- La Biennale di Venezia.
  - Nauman: Readings (Box 22, Folder 10)
    Photocopies of articles and bibliographies.
  - Nauman 2 Do (Box 23, Folder 1)
    To do lists, correspondence concerning edits, and a CD with a Word file of the book.
  - Nauman: Visuals (Box 23, Folder 2-4)
    Materials include postcards, Mapping the Studio II booklet, Flayed Earth/Flayed Self (Skin/Sink) publication for exhibition at the Nicholas Wilder Gallery, four CDs and a flash drive of images.
    4 CDs and 1 flash drive
  - Nauman: Misc. documents, 2008 (Box 23, Folder 5)
    Proposal for the Nauman book and a Sperone Westwater press release for Bruce Nauman: Drawings for Installations, his ninth solo exhibition with the gallery.
  - Nauman MSS: To Print CD-R (Box 23, Folder 6)
    This CD-R stores an electronic copy of Plagens' Nauman manuscript.
    1 CD-R
- Correspondence, 1972-2013
  This series includes personal and professional correspondence.
  - Correspondence, 1972-2006 (Box 24, Folder 1-6)
    Folder 1 includes letters from Ron Linden and actor Jack MacGowran.
    Folder 2 includes letters from Walter Gabrielson, Doug Hilson, Merwin Belin, George Plagens, Ron Linden, Jayne Plagens, M. Louise Stanley, John Coplans, Brenda Richardson, Isabel McIlvain, Cynthia Maughan and Peter Schjeldahl.
    Folder 3 includes letters from Laurie Fendrich, Phoebe Plagens, Adrian Biddell, George Plagens, Walter Gabrielson, Dave Hickey, Jayne Plagens, M. Kenneth Suddleson, Joseph D. Masheck, Bert Irvin, Felicitas Wetter, Marilyn Baxter, Doug Hilson and Merwin Belin.
    Folder 4 includes art writing correspondence.
    Folder 5 includes letters from Ron Linden, Walter Gabrielson, John Coplans, Jim Lee, Clarence Morgan, Marina Faust, Bill Pigman, Merwin Belin, Brenda Richardson and Johannes Lacher.
    Folder 6 includes letters from Ron Linden, Richard de Mille, John L. Garrett, Walter Gabrielson and George Plagens. Correspondence from George Plagens includes clippings and family photos.
  - Art/Writing Biz, 1996-2013 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    Correspondence and attached agreements concerning publishing rights.
  - A Drama In Your Mailbox Production postcards, 1997-2004 (Box 25, Folder 2)
    These humorous postcards are from Doug Hilson, founder and director of Doug's Museum of which Plagens said, "Most real museums worry about fake art. Doug's Museum is a fake museum that worries about real art."
  - About Painting, 2002-2003 (Box 25, Folder 3-4)
    About Painting was Plagens' idea for a painting focused art magazine that could branch out into history, chemistry, iconography and market. Plagens was working with a graphic designer, publications person and reaching out to writers, including John Updike who were interested in contributing to this publication. Adding "About" to the title was Laurie Fendrich's idea in order to move it to the top of alphabetical journal listings. They tried to raise two million dollars to start it up but struggled to sell the idea of an art magazine confined to painting.
    Folder 3 contains email correspondence and Plagens' About Painting press card.
    Folder 4 contains a trademark search report.
  - T-shirt, 2007 (Box 25, Folder 5)
    Email correspondence from Plagens discusses a t-shirt gift list for the holidays and black widow spider images from the jacket of Eric Ambler's 1940 spy novel which were used for the t-shirt design. One leg of the spider splayed out too much, so Plagens eliminated it and created a seven-legged spider for his t-shirt design.
  - Auburn cards (Box 25, Folder 6)
    Two Auburn University thank you cards are signed by students who appreciated Plagens' visit to their class.
  - Warhol/Creative Capital Grant floppies (Box 25, Folder 7)
    Correspondence, proposals and images.
- Lectures, circa 1980-2009
  This series includes annotated typescripts of lectures, slides, a program and posters.
  - This is About Formalist Painting in L.A. slides, circa 1980 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    Slides used for a lecture Plagens gave at UCLA Extension in which he never spoke, but experimented with a purely visual talk. Plagens describes abstract painting in the context of Los Angeles through this series of 19 slides which capture his humorous descriptions written in black ink on white posters.
  - GIGS floppies, 1994-2001 (Box 26, Folder 2)
    Documentation of Plagens' lectures.
  - Lecture notes (Box 26, Folder 3-4)
    Materials include typed lectures and panel discussion notes with Plagens' annotations for presentations at USC, Columbia Columbia College, the Jewish Museum, the National Council on Education for the Ceramic Arts (NCECA) conference and the Southeastern College Art Conference (SECAC) Annual Meeting. His USC Roski School of Art and Design lecture, "A Simple Country Painter" is in folder 3.
  - CAEA conference program, 2002 (Box 26, Folder 5)
    Shifting Perspectives, the Colorado Art Education Association (CAEA) Fall conference program features keynote speakers Peter Plagens and Laurie Fendrich.
  - The Absolute Truth CD-R, 2008 February 6 (Box 26, Folder 6)
    Recording of Plagens' "The Absolute Truth about Contemporary Art" lecture at the New York Studio School.
    One CD-R
  - Peter Plagens posters, 2009 (Box 36, Folder 6)
    Three full color posters announce Plagens' lectures at Southern Illinois University Carbondale (SIUC) for its School of Art and Design's Painter/Art Critic Lecture Series.
- Course Materials, 1985-2011
  This series includes course evaluations, syllabi, lecture notes, assignments, assessments, readings, discussion questions and student papers from courses taught at Princeton University, Hofstra University, Middlebury College and New York University.
  - Princeton evaluations, 1985-1986 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    Cumulative course evaluations by Princeton University students for Plagens' Visual Arts 304 course.
  - Hofstra class final project, 1986 (Box 27, Folder 2)
    A photocopy of Plagens' final project assignment for Hofstra classes FA 5 and FA 14 includes size, materials, description, purpose, method and criteria for evaluation.
  - HARC 0307 Archives, 2005 (Box 27, Folder 3-4)
    Contemporary Art and Criticism course materials include a syllabus, timelines, lecture notes, photocopies of readings and lists of questions.
  - Colloquium, 2005 (Box 27, Folder 5)
    Readings, timelines and a syllabus for Plagens' Middlebury College Faculty Colloquium entitled, "The Anxious Object of Modern Art: Questioning the work of art from Cubism through Performance Art."
  - Hofstra Seminar Reading, 2008 (Box 27, Folder 6-7)
    Course materials for Plagens' Hofstra University seminar, "The Artist's Practice" include photocopies of readings, handwritten lecture notes and a syllabus.
  - NYU, 2009 (Box 27, Folder 8)
    Plagens' Seminar in Art Criticism course materials include correspondence from NYU, handwritten and typed notes, discussion questions, quizzes, student course evaluations and a syllabus.
  - NYU, 2011 (Box 28, Folder 1-2)
    Plagens' Seminar in Art Criticism course materials include photocopies of readings, typed lecture notes, student papers and a syllabus.
- Photos and Slides, 1958-2014
  This series is comprised of personal photos and slides.
  - JMHS prom after party photocopy, 1958 June (Box 29, Folder 1)
    One photocopy of a high school photograph captures Plagens and friends at Moulin Rouge, a nightclub in Hollywood that hosted the John Marshall High School after-prom dinner. Plagens is seated at the front of the table dressed in a white suit with a plaid bow tie and cummerbund.
  - Personal slides, 1964-1999 (Box 29, Folder 2-3)
    Folder 2: Slides include images of his studios in Los Angeles on Union Street, 239 South Los Angeles Street and in Pasadena as well as his studios in Austin, Texas, Durham, North Carolina, Johnson, Vermont and New York. There are also images of Peter and children: Paul Wisdom Plagens, Sybil Wisdom, and Phoebe Plagens. Other slides capture images of Peter and his wife Laurie Fendrich, best friend Walter Gabrielson, gallerist Nancy Hoffman, George Green, Robert Pincus-Witten, Jim DeFrance, Sydney Littenberg, Johannes Lacher, Mitchell Kahan, David Gates and Merwin Belin.
    Folder 3: Slides include images of Peter and his wife Laurie Fendrich, their daughter Phoebe, and Plagens's studios in Los Angeles, Texas and New York.
  - Personal photos, 1979-1996 (Box 29, Folder 4)
    Color photographs include images of the exterior and interior of Plagens' 239 S. Los Angeles Street studio, Peter and Ed Ruscha, Laurie Fendrich, Jayne Plagens, Johannes Lacher, George Plagens, son Paul Wisdom Plagens, daughters Sybil Wisdom and Phoebe Plagens, George Garcia and Peter's sister Pamela Garcia, Merwin Belin, Doug Hilson, David Gates, Ron Linden and a Polaroid portrait of Plagens signed by Suzanne Paul.
  - Peter and Phoebe photos, 1984 (Box 29, Folder 5)
    Two black and white photos of Plagens and his daughter.
  - "Sep Bye to LA" photos, circa 1985 (Box 29, Folder 6)
    Three photo album pages feature images of Peter's daughter Phoebe in Little Tokyo, at his studio in downtown Los Angeles and at the Hollywood Bowl.
  - Paul Wisdom Plagens head shots, undated (Box 29, Folder 7)
    Black and white head shots of Peter's son Paul Wisdom Plagens.
  - Dora Maar House residency photos, 2009 April 30-May 31 (Box 29, Folder 8)
    Color photos of Plagens and Laurie Fendrich, in front of the Dora Maar House in Southern France.
  - Peter photo, 2010 (Box 29, Folder 9)
    One black and white image from a Hofstra University publication of Plagens teaching.
  - Ruth Bachofner Gallery opening photo, 2014 (Box 29, Folder 10)
    One color photograph of Ron Linden, Elizabeth Medina and Plagens in the Ruth Bachofner Gallery at the Bergamot Station Art Center.
- Notebooks and Datebooks, 1995-2013
  This series is comprised of notebooks, datebooks, to-do lists, a mailing list and address book.
  - Notebooks and to do lists, circa 2007-2013 (Box 30)
    Two notebooks filled with ideas and to do lists written on notecards and Post-Its.
  - Datebooks, 1996-2004, 2008-2012 (Box 31, Folder 1-15)
    These 15 annual datebooks are heavily annotated by Plagens.